Chapter 5. Riddles in the Dark.
When Bilbo opened his eyes, he wondered if he had, for it was just as dark as
with them shut. No one was anywhere near him. Just imagine his fright. He could
hear nothing, see nothing, and he could feel nothing except the stone of the
floor. Very slowly he got up and groped about on all fours till he touched the
wall of the tunnel. But neither up nor down could he find anything. nothing at
all. No sign of goblins, no sign of dwarves. His head was swimming, and he
was far from certain, even of the direction they had been going in when he
had his fall. He guessed as well as he could, and crawled along for a good way,
till suddenly his hand met what felt like a tiny ring of cold metal lying on
the floor of the tunnel. It was a turning point in his career, but he did
not know it. He put the ring in his pocket almost without thinking.
Certainly it did not seem of any particular use at the moment. He did not
go much further, but sat down on the cold floor and gave himself up to
complete miserableness for a long while.
He thought of himself frying bacon and eggs in his own kitchen at home, for he
could feel inside that it was high time for some meal or other, but that only
made him miserable. He could not think what to do, nor could he think what had
happened, or why he had been left behind, or why, if he had been left
behind, the goblins had not caught him, or even why his head was so sore. The
truth was, he had been lying quiet, out of sight and out of mind, in a very dark
corner for a long while. After some time he felt for his pipe. It was not broken,
and that was something. Then he felt for his pouch, and there was some tobacco in
it, and that was something more. Then he felt for matches, and he could not find
any at all, and that shattered his hopes completely, just as well for him, as he
agreed when he came to his senses.
Goodness knows what the striking of matches and the smell of tobacco would
have brought on him out of dark holes in that horrible place. Still at the moment
he felt very crushed. But in slapping all his pockets and feeling all around
himself for matches, his hand came on the hilt of his little sword the little
dagger that he got from the trolls and that he had quite forgotten. Nor
fortunately had the goblins noticed it as he wore it inside his breaches.
Now he drew it out. It shone pale and dim before his eyes. Sword is an Elvish
blade, too, he thought. And goblins are not very near, and yet not far enough.
But somehow he was comforted. It was rather splendid to be wearing a blade
made in Gondolan for the goblin wars of which so many songs had sung, and also
he had noticed that such weapons made a great impression on goblins that came
upon them suddenly. "Go back, he thought, no good at all. Go sideways,
impossible. Go forward. Only thing to do. On we go. So up he got and trotted
along with his little sword held in front of him and one hand feeling the
wall and his heart all of a patter and a pitter. Now certainly Bilbo was in what
is called a tight place. But you must remember it was not quite so tight for
him as it would have been for me or for you. Hobbits are not quite like ordinary
people. And after all, if their holes are nice, cheery places and properly
aired, quite different from the tunnels of the goblins, still they are more used
to tunneling than we are, and they do not easily lose their sense of direction
underground. Not when their heads have recovered from being bumped. Also, they
can move very quietly and hide easily, and recover wonderfully from falls and
bruises. and they have a fund of wisdom and wise sayings that men had mostly
never heard or have forgotten long ago.
I should not have liked to have been in Mr. Baggin's place all the same. The
tunnel seemed to have no end. All he knew was that it was still going down
pretty steadily and keeping in the same direction in spite of a twist and a turn
or two. There were passages leading off to the side every now and then, as he
knew by the glimmer of his sword, or could feel with his hand on the wall. of
these he took no notice except to hurry past for fear of goblins or half-
imagined dark things coming out of them.
On and on he went and down and down, and still he heard no sound of anything
except the occasional were of a bat by his ears, which startled him at first,
till it became too frequent to bother about. I do not know how long he kept on
like this, hating to go on, not daring to stop on, on until he was tired than
tired. It seemed like all the way to tomorrow and over it to the days beyond.
Suddenly, without any warning, he trotted splash into water. Oh, it was
icy cold. That pulled him up sharp and short. He did not know whether it was
just a pool in the path or the edge of an underground stream that crossed the
passage or the brink of a deep dark subterranean lake. The sword was hardly
shining at all. He stopped and he could hear, when he listened hard, drops drip
drip dripping from an unseen roof into the water below. But there seemed to no
other sort of sound. So it is a pool or a lake and not an underground river, he
thought. Still he did not dare to wade out into the darkness. He could not swim
and he thought too of nasty slimy things with big bulging blind eyes wriggling in
the water. There are strange things living in the pools and lakes in the
hearts of mountains. Fish whose fathers swam in. Goodness only knows how many
years ago and never swam out again while their eyes grew bigger and bigger and
bigger from trying to see in the blackness. Also, there are other things
more slimy than fish. Even in the tunnels and caves the goblins have made
for themselves, there are other things living unbeknown to them that have
sneaked in from outside to lie up in the dark. Some of these caves, too, go back
in their beginnings to ages before the goblins, who only widened them and
joined them up with passages, and the original owners are still there in odd
corners, slinking and nosing about. Deep down here by the dark water lived old
Gollum, a small slimy creature. I don't know where he came from, nor who or what
he was. He was Gollum as dark as dark as darkness, except for two big round, pale
eyes in his thin face. He had a little boat, and he rode about quite quietly on
the lake, for lake it was wide and deep and deadly cold. He paddled it with
large feet dangling over the side, but never a ripple did he make. Not he. He
was looking out of his pale lap-like eyes for blind fish, which he grabbed
with his long fingers as quick as thinking. He liked meat, too. Goblin, he
thought good when he could get it, but he took care they never found him out.
He just throttled them from behind, if they ever came down alone, anywhere near
the edge of the water while he was prowling about. They very seldom did,
for they had a feeling that something unpleasant was lurking down there, down
at the very roots of the mountain. They had come on the lake when they were
tunneling down long ago, and they found they could go no further. So there the
road ended in that direction, and there was no reason to go that way, unless the
great goblins sent them. Sometimes he took a fancy for fish from the lake, and
sometimes neither goblin nor fish came back. Actually, Gallum lived on a slimy
island of rock in the middle of the lake. He was watching Bilbo now from the
distance with his pale eyes like telescopes. Bilbo could not see him, but
he was wondering a lot about Bilbo, for he could see that he was no goblin at
all. Gollum got into his boat and shot off from the island, while Bilbo was
sitting on the brink altogether flumxed, and at the end of his way and his wits,
suddenly up came Gollum, and whispered and hissed, "Bless us, and splash us, my
preciouses. I guess it's a choice feast.
At least a tasty morsel it make us, Gollum." And when he said Gollum, he
made a horrible swallowing noise in his throat. That is how he got his name,
though he always called himself my precious.
The hobbit jumped nearly out of his skin when the hiss came in his ears, and he
suddenly saw the pale eyes sticking out at him. "Who are you?" he said,
thrusting his dagger in front of him.
"What is he, my precious?" whispered Gollum, who always spoke to himself
through never having anyone else to speak to. This is what he had come to
find out, for he was not really very hungry at the moment, only curious.
Otherwise, he would have grabbed first and whispered afterwards.
"I am Mr. Bil Baggins. I have lost the dwarves, and I have lost the wizard, and
I don't know where I am, and I don't want to know. If only I can get away."
What he got in his hands is said Gollum looking at the sword which he did not
quite like. A sword, a blade which came out of Gondolan. Sis, said Gollum, and
became quite polite. Perhaps yet they sits here in chats with it a bitsy, my
precious. It likes riddles. Perhaps it does, does it? He was anxious to appear
friendly. At any rate, for the moment, and until he found out more about the
sword in the hobbit, whether he was quite alone really, whether he was good
to eat, and whether Gollum was really hungry, riddles were all he could think
of. Asking them and sometimes guessing them had been the only game he had ever
played with other funny creatures sitting in their holes in the long long
ago before he lost all his friends and was driven away alone and crept down
down into the dark under the mountains.
Very well, said Bilbo, who was anxious to agree until he found out more about
the creature, whether he was quite alone, whether he was fierce or hungry,
and whether he was a friend of the goblins.
You asked first, he said, because he had not had time to think of a riddle. So
Gallum hissed. What has roots as nobody sees is taller than trees up a co, and
yet never grows? Easy, said Bilbo.
Mountain, I suppose. Does it gussy? It must have a competition with us, my
precious. If precious asks and it doesn't answer, we eats it, my
preciouses. If it asks us and we doesn't answer, then we does what it wants. E,
we shows it the way out. Yes.
All right, said Bilbo, not daring to disagree, and nearly bursting his brain
to think of riddles that could save him from being eaten.
30 white horses on a red hell. First they champ, then they stamp, then they
stand still. That was all he could think of to ask the idea of eating was rather
on his mind. It was rather an old one, too, and Gollum knew the answer as well
as you do. Chestnuts, chestnuts, he hissed. Teeth, teeth, my precious, but
we has only six. Then he asked his second. Voiceless it cries, wingless
flutters, toothless bites, mouthless mutters.
Half a moment, cried Bilbo, who was still thinking uncomfortably about
eating. Fortunately, he had once heard something rather like this before, and
getting his wits back, he thought of the answer. Wind. Wind, of course, he said,
and he was so pleased that he made up one on the spot. This will puzzle the
nasty little underground creature, he thought. An eye in a blue face, saw an
eye in a green face. That eye is like to
this eye, said the first eye, but in low place, not in high place.
Cess s said Gollum. He had been underground a long, long time and was
forgetting this sort of thing. But just as Bilbo was beginning to hope that the
wretch would not be able to answer, Gollum brought up memories of ages and
ages and ages before when he lived with his grandmother in a hole in a bank by a
river. Sis, my precious, he said, "Son, on the daisies, it means it does." But
these ordinary above ground everyday sort of riddles were tiring for him.
Also, they reminded him of days when he had been less lonely and sleeky and
nasty, and that put him out of temper.
What is more, they made him hungry. So this time he tried something a bit more
difficult and more unpleasant.
It cannot be seen, cannot be felt, cannot be heard, cannot be smelt. It
lies behind stars and under hills and empty holes it fills. It comes first and
follows after. Ends life kills laughter.
Unfortunately for Gollum, Bilbo had heard that sort of thing before, and the
answer was all around him anyway. Dark, he said without even scratching his
head, or putting on his thinking cap. A box without hinges, key, or lid, yet
golden treasure inside his head. He asked to gain time until he could think
of a really hard one. This, he thought, a dreadfully easy chestnut, though he
had not asked it in the usual words, but it proved a nasty poser for Gollum. He
hissed to himself, and still he did not answer. He whispered and spluted. After
some, while Bilbo became impatient.
"Well, what is it?" he said. "The answer's not a kettle boiling over, as
you seem to think from the noise you are making. Give us a chance. Let it give us
a chance, my precious ises. S. Well, said Bilbo, after giving him a long
chance, what about your guess? But suddenly Gollum remembered from nests
long ago, and sitting under the riverbank, teaching his grandmother,
teaching his grandmother to suck. Exes, he hissed. Eggs as it is, then he asked.
alive without breath, as cold as death, never thirsty, ever drinking, all in
male, never clinking.
He also, in his turn, thought this was a dreadfully easy one, because he was
always thinking of the answer, but he could not remember anything better at
the moment. He was so flustered by the egg question.
All the same, it was a poser for poor Bilbo, who never had anything to do with
the water, if he could help it. I imagine you know the answer, of course,
or can guess it as easy as winking, since you are sitting comfortably at
home, and have not the danger of being eaten to disturb your thinking.
Bilbo sat and cleared his throat once or twice, but no answer came. After a
while, Gollum began to hiss with pleasure to himself, "Is it nice, my
precious? Is it juicy? Is it scrumptiously crunchable? He began to
peer at Bilbo out of the darkness.
Half a moment, said the Hobbit, shivering.
I gave you a good long chance just now.
It must make haste. Haste? said Gollum, beginning to climb out of his boat onto
the shore to get at Bilbo. But when he put his long webbby foot in the water, a
fish jumped out in a fright and fell on Bilbo's toes. "Ah," he said, "it is cold
and clammy, and so he guessed." "Fish!
Fish!" he cried. "It is fish." Gollum was dreadfully disappointed. But Bilbo
asked another riddle as quick as ever he could, so that Gollum had to get back
into his boat and think. No legs lay on one leg. Two legs sat near on three
legs. Four legs got some. It was not really the right time for this riddle,
but Bilbo was in a hurry. Gollum might have had some trouble guessing it if he
had asked it at another time. As it was, talking a fish, no legs, was not so very
difficult, and after that the rest was easy. Fish on a little table, man at
table sitting on a stool. The cat has the bones. That of course is the answer.
And Gollum soon gave it. Then he thought the time had come to ask something hard
and horrible. This is what he said. This thing all things devours. Birds, beasts,
trees, flowers, gnaws iron, bites steel, grinds hard stones to meal, slays king,
ruins town, and beats high mountain down.
Poor Bilbo sat in the dark thinking of all the horrible names of all the giants
and ogres he had ever heard told of in tales, but not one of them had done all
these things. He had a feeling that the answer was quite different and that he
ought to know it, but he could not think of it. He began to get frightened, and
that is bad for thinking. Gllum began to get out of his boat. He flapped into the
water and paddled to the bank. Bilbo could see his eyes coming towards him.
His tongue seemed to stick in his mouth.
He wanted to shout out, "Give me more time! Give me time!"
But all that came out with a sudden squeal was, "Time! Time!" Bilbo was
saved by pure luck, for that, of course, was the answer. Gollum was disappointed
once more, and now he was getting angry and also tired of the game.
It had made him very hungry indeed. This time he did not go back to the boat. He
sat down in the dark by Bilbo. That made the hobbit most dreadfully uncomfortable
and scattered his wits. It's got to ask as a castion, my precious. Yes, yes,
yes. Just one more question to guess.
Yes, yes, said Gollum. But Bilbo simply could not think of any question with
that nasty wet cold thing sitting next to him. and pawing and poking him. He
scratched himself. He pinched himself.
Still he could not think of anything.
"Ask us, ask us," said Gollum. Bilbo pinched himself and slapped himself. He
gripped on his little sword. He even felt in his pocket with his other hand.
There he found the ring he had picked up in the passage and forgotten about.
"What have I got in my pocket?" he said aloud. He was talking to himself, but
Gollum thought it was a riddle, and he was frightfully upset.
Not fair. Not fair, he hissed. It isn't fair, my precious, is it to ask us what
it's got in its nasty little pockets is.
Bilbo, seeing what had happened, and having nothing better to ask, stuck to
his question. What have I got in my pocket? He said louder.
SS his gull. It must give us three guesses as my precious. Three guesses is
very well guess away, said Bilbo.
Hanses, said Gollum. Wrong, said Bilbo, who had luckily just taken his hand out
again. Guess again.
SS, said Gollum, more upset than ever.
He thought of all the things he kept in his own pockets. fishbones, goblins
teeth, wet shells, a bit of batwing, a sharp stone to sharpen his fangs on, and
other nasty things. He tried to think what other people kept in their pockets.
"Nice," he said at last. "Wrong," said Bilbo, who had lost his some time ago.
"Last guess."
Now Gollum was in a much worse state than when Bilbo had asked him the egg
question. He hissed and spluttered and rocked himself backwards and forwards
and slapped his feet on the floor and wriggled and squirmed,
but still he did not dare to waste his last guess. "Come on," said Bilbo. "I am
waiting." He tried to sound bold and cheerful, but he did not feel at all
sure how the game was going to end, whether Gollum guessed right or not.
"Times up," he said. string or nothing," shrieked Gollum, which was not quite
fair working in two guesses at once.
"Both wrong!" cried Bilbo, very much relieved, and he jumped at once to his
feet, put his back to the nearest wall, and held out his little sword. He knew,
of course, that the riddle game was sacred and of immense antiquity, and
even wicked creatures were afraid to cheat when they played at it. But he
felt he could not trust this slimy thing to keep any promise at a pinch. Any
excuse would do for him to slide out of it, and after all, that last question
had not been a genuine riddle according to the ancient laws. But at any rate,
Garland did not at once attack him. He could see the sword in Bilbo's hand. He
sat still, shivering and whispering. At last, Bilbo could wait no longer.
Well, he said, what about your promise?
I want to go. You must show me the way.
Did we say so, Precious? Show the nasty little baggins the way out. Yes, yes,
but what has it got in its pocketses?
Eh, not string, precious, but not nothing. Oh, no, Gollum.
Never you mind, said Bilbo. A promise is a promise.
Cross it is impatient, precious, hissed Gollum. But it must wait. Yes, it must.
We can't go up the tunnel so hasty. We must go and get some things first. Yes,
things to help us.
Well, hurry up, said Bilbo, relieved to think of Gollum going away. He thought
he was just making an excuse and did not mean to come back. What was Gollum
talking about? What useful thing could he keep out on the dark lake? But he was
wrong. Gollum did mean to come back. He was angry now and hungry, and he was a
miserable, wicked creature, and already he had a plan. Not far away was his
island, of which Bilbo knew nothing. And there, in his hiding place, he kept a
few wretched oddments and one very beautiful thing. Very beautiful, very
wonderful. He had a ring, a golden ring, a precious ring. My birthday present, he
whispered to himself, as he had often done in the endless dark days. That's
what we want now. Yes, we wants it. He wanted it because it was a ring of
power, and if you slipped that ring on your finger, you were invisible. Only in
the full sunlight could you be seen, and then only by your shadow. and that would
be shaky and faint. My birthday present, it came to me on my birthday, my
precious. So he had always said to himself, but who knows how Gollum came
by that present ages ago in the old days when such rings were still at large in
the world. Perhaps even the master who ruled him could not have said. Gllum
used to wear it at first till it tired
him, and then he kept it in a pouch next
to his skin till it gled him. And now
usually he hid it in a hole in the rock on his island and was always going back
to look at it. And still sometimes he put it on when he could not bear to be
parted from it any longer, or when he was very, very hungry and tired of fish.
Then he would creep along dark passages looking for stray goblins. He might even
venture into places where the torches were lit and made his eyes blink and
smart, for he would be safe. Oh yes, quite safe. No one would see him. No one
would notice him till he had his fingers on their throat. Only a few hours ago he
had worn it and caught a small goblin imp.
How it squeaked. He still had a bone or two left to naw, but he wanted something softer.
Quite safe, yes, he whispered to himself. It won't see us, will it, my
precious? No, it won't see us, and its nasty little sword will be useless. Yes,
quite. That is what was in his wicked little mind as he slipped suddenly from
Bilbo's side and flapped back to his boat and went off into the dark. Bilbo
thought he had heard the last of him.
Still he waited a while, for he had no idea how to find his way out alone.
Suddenly he heard a screech. It sent a shiver down his back. Gollum was cursing
and wailing away in the gloom, not very far off by the sound of it. He was on
his island, scrabbling here and there, searching and seeking in vain. Where is
it? Where is it? Bilbo heard him crying.
Lost it is my precious lost. Lost.
Curses and crushes. My precious is lost.
What's the matter? Bilbo called. What have you lost?
It mustn't ask us, shrieked Gollum. Not its business. No, Gollum. It's lost.
Gollum. Gollum. Gollum.
Well, so am I, cried Bilbo. And I want to get unlost, and I won the game, and
you promised. So come along. Come and let me out, and then go on with your
looking. Utterly miserable as Gollum sounded, Bilbo could not find much pity
in his heart, and he had a feeling that anything Gollum wanted so much could
hardly be something good. Come along, he shouted.
No, not yet, Precious, Gollum answered.
We must search for it. It's lost, Gollum. But you never guessed my last
question, and you promised, said Bilbo.
Never guessed, said Gollum. Then suddenly out of the gloom came a sharp
kiss. What has it got in its pocketses?
Tell us that. It must tell first. As far as Bilbo knew, there was no particular
reason why he should not tell. Gllum's mind had jumped to a guess quicker than
his. Naturally, forgum had brooded for ages on this one thing, and he was
always afraid of it being stolen. But Bilbo was annoyed at the delay. After
all, he had won the game pretty fairly at a horrible risk. Answers were to be
guessed, not given, he said. But he wasn't a fair question, said Gollum. Not
a riddle, Precious. No. Oh, well, if it's a matter of ordinary questions,
Bilbo replied, "Then I asked one first.
What have you lost? Tell me that." What has it got in its pocketses? The sound
came hissing louder and sharper, and as he looked towards it, to his alarm,
Bilbo now saw two small points of light peering at him. As suspicion grew in
Gollum's mind, the light of his eyes burned with a pale flame. "What have you
lost?" Belmo persisted.
But now the light in Gollum's eyes had become a green fire, and it was coming
swiftly nearer. Gollum was in his boat again, paddling wildly back to the dark
shore, and such a rage of loss and suspicion was in his heart, that no
sword had any more terror for him. Bilbo could not guess what had maddened the
wretched creature, but he saw that all was up, and that Gallum meant to murder
him at any rate. Just in time, he turned and ran blindly back up the dark passage
down which he had come, keeping close to the wall and feeling it with his left hand.
What has it got in its pockets is? He heard the hiss loud behind him and the
splash as Gollum leapt from his boat.
What have I, I wonder, he said to himself as he panted and stumbled along.
He put his left hand in his pocket. The ring felt very cold as it quietly
slipped onto his groping forefinger.
The hiss was close behind him. He turned now and saw Gollum's eyes like small
green laps coming up the slope.
Terrified, he tried to run faster, but suddenly he struck his toes on a snag in
the floor and fell flat with his little sword under him. In a moment, Gollum was
on him. But before Bilbo could do anything or cover his breath, pick
himself up, or wave his sword, Gollum passed by, taking no notice of him,
cursing and whispering as he ran. What could it mean? Gollum could see in the
dark. Bilbo could see the light of his eyes paly shining even from behind.
Painfully he got up and sheaved his sword, which was now glowing faintly
again. Then very cautiously he followed.
There seemed nothing else to do. It was no good crawling back down to Gollum's
water. Perhaps if he followed him, Gollum might lead him to some way of
escape without meaning to. Curse it.
Curse it. Curse it, hissed Column. Curse the Baggins. It's gone. What has it got
in its pocketses? Oh, we guess. We guess, my precious. He's found it. Yes,
he must have. My birthday present. Bilbo pricked up his ears. He was at last
beginning to guess himself. He hurried a little, getting as close as he dared
behind Gollum, who was still going quickly, not looking back, but turning
his head from side to side, as Bilbo could see from the faint glimmer on the
walls. My birthday present. Curse it.
How did we lose it, my precious? Yes, that's it. When we came this way last,
when we twisted that nasty young squeaker. That's it. Curse it. It's that
from us after all these ages and ages it's gone. Gollum.
Suddenly Gollum sat down and began to weep. A whistling and gurgling sound
horrible to listen to. Bilbo halted and flattened himself against the tunnel wall.
After a while, Gollum stopped weeping and began to talk. He seemed to be
having an argument with himself.
It's no good going back there to search.
No, we doesn't remember all the places we visited, and it's no use. The Baggins
has got it in its pocketses. The nasty noser has found it, we says. We guesses,
precious, only guesses. We can't know till we find the nasty creature and
squeezes it. But it doesn't know what the present can do, does it? It'll just
keep it in its pocketses.
It doesn't know, and it can't go far.
It's lost itself, the nasty, nosy thing.
It doesn't know the way out. It said so.
It said so, yes, but it's Trixie. It doesn't say what it means. It won't say
what it's got in its pocketses. It knows. It knows a way in. It must know a
way out. Yes, it's off to the back door.
To the back door. That's it. The goblins will catch it then. It can't get out
that way. Precious sis. Gollum. Goblins is Yes. But if it's got the present, our
precious present, then goblinsies will get it. Gollum. They'll find it. They'll
find out what it does.
We shall ever be safe again. Never.
Gollum.
One of the goblinsies will put it on and then no one will see him.
He'll be there but not seen.
Not even our clever eyes will notice him.
And he'll creepy and catch us. Gollum Gollum. Then let's stop talking,
precious, and make haste. If the Baggins has gone that way, we must go quick and
see. Go. Not far now. Make haste. With the spring, Gollum got up and started
shambling off at a great pace. Bilbo hurried after him, still cautiously,
though his chief fear now was of tripping on another snag and falling
with a noise. His head was in a whirl of hope and wonder. It seemed that the ring
he had was a magic ring. It made you invisible. He had heard of such things,
of course, in old old tales, but it was hard to believe that he really had found
one by accident. Still there it was.
Gollum with his bright eyes had passed him by only a yard to one side. On they
went, Gollum flip-fpping ahead, hissing and cursing, Bilbo behind going as
softly as a hobbit can. Soon they came to places where, as Bil had noticed, on
the way down, side passages opened this way and that, Gollum began at once to
count them. One left, yes. One right.
Yes. Two right. Yes. Yes. Two left. Yes.
Yes. And so on and on. As the count grew, he slowed down, and he began to
get shaky and weepy, for he was leaving the water further and further behind,
and he was getting afraid. Goblins might be about, and he had lost his ring. At
last he stopped by a low opening on their left as they went up. Seven right.
Yes. Six left. Yes. He whispered. This is it. This is the way to the back door.
Yes. Here's the passage.
He peered in and shrank back. But we doesn't go in, precious. No, we don't.
Goblins is down there. Lots of goblins is. We smells them. Sis,
what shall we do? Curse them and crush them. We must wait here, precious. wait
a bit and see. So they came to a dead stop. Gollum had brought Bilbo to the
way out after all, but Bilbo could not get in. There was Gollum sitting humped
up right in the opening, and his eyes gleamed cold in his head as he swayed it
from side to side between his knees.
Bilbo crept away from the wall more quietly than a mouse, but Gollum
stiffened at once and sniffed, and his eyes went green. He hissed softly, but
menacingly, he could not see the hobbit, but now he was on the alert, and he had
other senses that the darkness had sharpened, hearing and smell. He seemed
to be crouched right down with his flat hand spled on the floor, and his head
thrusted out, nose almost to the stone.
Though he was only a black shadow in the gleam of his own eyes, Bilbo could see
or feel that he was tense as a bowring gathered for a spring. Bilbo almost
stopped breathing and went stiff himself. He was desperate. He must get
away out of this horrible darkness while he had any strength left. He must fight.
He must stab the foul thing. Put its eyes out. Kill it. It meant to kill him.
No, not a fair fight. He was invisible now. Gollum had no sword. Gollum had no
sword. Gollum had not actually threatened to kill him or tried to yet,
and he was miserable, alone, lost. A sudden understanding, a pity mixed with
horror, welled up in Bilbo's heart, a glimpse of endless unmarked days without
light or hope of betterment, hard stone, cold fish, sneaking and whispering. All
these thoughts passed in a flash of a second. He trembled, and then quite
suddenly, in another flash, as if lifted by a new strength and resolve, he
leaped. No great leap for a man, but a leap in the dark. Straight over Gollum's
head, he jumped 7 ft forward and three in the air. Indeed, had he known it, he
only just missed cracking his skull on the low arch of the passage.
Gollum threw himself backwards and grabbed as the hobbit flew over him, but
too late his hand snapped on thin air, and Bilbo, falling fair on his sturdy
feet, sped off down the new tunnel. He did not turn to see what Gollum was
doing. There was a hissing and cursing almost at his heels at first. Then it
stopped. All at once there came a blood curdling shriek filled with hatred and
despair. Gllum was defeated. He dared go no further. He had lost lost his prey
and lost too the only thing he had ever cared for his precious. The cry brought
Bilbo's heart to his mouth but still he held on now faint as an echo but
menacing. The voice came behind.
Thief thief thief Baggins. We hate it.
We hate it. We hate it. We hate it forever.
Then there was a silence, but that too seemed menacing to Bilbo. If goblins are
so near that he smelt them, he thought, then thou have heard his shrieking and cursing.
Careful now, or this way will lead you to worse things. The passage was low and
roughly made. It was not too difficult for the hobbit, except when, in spite of
all care, he stubbed his poor toes again, several times on nasty, jagged stones in the floor.
A bit low for goblins, at least for the big ones, thought Bilbo, not knowing
that even the big ones, the orcs of the mountains, go along at a great speed,
stooping low with their hands almost on the ground. Soon the passage that had
been sloping down, began to go up again, and after a while it climbed steeply.
That slowed Bilbo down, but at last the slope stopped. The passage turned a
corner and dipped down again, and there, at the bottom of a short incline, he saw
filtering round another corner a glimpse of light. Not red light as a fire or
lantern, but a pale out of door sort of light. Then Bilbo began to run.
Scuttling as fast as his legs would carry him, he turned the last corner and
came suddenly right into an open space where the light, after all that time in
the dark, seemed dazzlingly bright.
Really, it was only a leak of sunshine and through a doorway where a great
door, a stone door, was left standing open. Bil blinked, and then suddenly he
saw the goblins. goblins in full armor with drawn swords sitting just inside
the door and watching it with wide eyes and watching the passage that led to it.
They were aroused, alert, ready for anything. They saw him sooner than he
saw them. Yes, they saw him.
They saw the re one from and went to sunb a pang of fear and loss like an
echo of Gollum's misery smoke bilbo and forgetting even to draw his sword he
struck his hands into his pockets and there was the ring still in his left
pocket and it slipped on his finger.
The goblins stopped short. They could not see a sign of him. He had vanished.
They yelled twice as loud as before, but not so delightedly.
Where is it? They cried. Go back up the passage, some shouted. This way, some
yelled. That way, others yelled. Look out for the door, bellowed the captain.
Whistles blew, armor clashed, swords rattled, goblins cursed and swore and
ran heather and thither, falling over one another and getting very angry.
There was a terrible outcry to do and disturbance.
Bilbo was dreadfully frightened, but he had the sense to understand what had
happened, and to sneak behind a big barrel which held drink for the goblin
guards, and so get out of the way, and avoid being bumped into, trampled to
death, or caught by field. "I must get to the door. I must get to the door," he
kept on saying to himself. But it was a long time before he ventured to try.
Then it was like a horrible game of blind man's buff. The place was full of
goblins running about, and the poor little hobbit dodged this way, and that
was knocked over by a goblin, who could not make out what he had bumped into,
scrambled away on all fours, slipped between the legs of the captain just in
time, got up, and ran for the door. It was still a jar, but a goblin had pushed
it nearly too. Bilbo struggled, but he could not move it. He tried to squeeze
through the crack. He squeezed and squeezed and he stuck. It was awful. His
buttons had got wedged on the edge of the door and the doorpost. He could see
outside into the open air. There were a few steps running down into a narrow
valley between tall mountains. The sun came out from behind a cloud and shone
bright on the outside of the door, but he could not get through. Suddenly, one
of the goblins inside shouted, "There is a shadow by the door. Something is outside."
Bilbo's height jumped into his mouth. He gave a terrific squirm. Buttons burst
off in all directions. He was through with a torn coat and waste coat, leaping
down the steps like a goat, while bewildered goblins were still picking up
his nice brass buttons on the doorstep.
Of course, they soon came down after him, hooding and hooing and hunting
among the trees, but they don't like the sun. It makes their legs wobble and
their heads giddy. They could not find Bilbo with the ring on, slipping in and
out of the shadow of the trees, running quick and quiet, and keeping out of the
sun. So soon they went back grumbling and cursing to guard the door.
Bilbo had escaped. Chapter 6. Out of the